<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vector-Databases on Jairaj Kumar | Software Engineer</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/vector-databases/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vector-Databases on Jairaj Kumar | Software Engineer</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 03:49:40 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/vector-databases/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Building Powerful Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) Applications with Vector Databases</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blogs/building_rag/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 03:49:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blogs/building_rag/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;building-powerful-retrieval-augmented-generation-rag-applications-with-vector-databases&#34;&gt;Building Powerful Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) Applications with Vector Databases&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs) like Google’s &lt;strong&gt;Gemini&lt;/strong&gt; have revolutionized how we interact with machines—capable of understanding prompts, generating diverse content formats, answering complex questions, and more. However, even the most sophisticated LLMs come with inherent limitations:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knowledge Cutoff:&lt;/strong&gt; They lack awareness of events or data developed after their training date.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hallucination Risk:&lt;/strong&gt; They may generate responses that are plausible-sounding but factually incorrect.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Access to Private Data:&lt;/strong&gt; They can’t natively access your proprietary documents, internal files, or niche knowledge bases.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is where &lt;strong&gt;Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)&lt;/strong&gt; comes in—a technique that enhances LLMs by grounding their responses in external, up-to-date, and domain-specific information. When paired with a &lt;strong&gt;vector database&lt;/strong&gt;, Gemini becomes a much more powerful tool for building intelligent, reliable, and context-aware applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
